A Guide to the Toole Family Papers 1860-1979
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Toole Family Papers 1860-1979
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4876-e
This collection consists of ca. 700 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Toole Papers were given to the library on September 14, 1979 by Mrs. B. Woodruff Weaver of Alexandria, Virginia, and bear no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers of the Toole family of Albemarle County, Virginia, and later of Washington, D.C. The earliest items are chiefly letters received by Mrs. Mary Jane Toole, after she moved to Washington in 1860 following the death of her husband, Virginia painter John Toole, until her death in 1902. Letters dating from 1926-1929 were chiefly written to her daughter, Alice Toole Barnes, and later correspondence, 1951-1979, is that of descendents of John Toole, including Mr. and Mrs. B. Woodruff Weaver.
The Jane Toole material consists chiefly of personal correspondence with family and friends whereas the Weaver items primarily pertain to Toole family genealogy and biographical information on John Toole, and include material relating to exhibitions of his work and the establishment of a John Toole Trust Fund at the University of Virginia, including two copies of the indenture for the Trust. Also included is a family photo album, several loose photographs, and two works of art by John Toole, a charcoal drawing of a woman and a watercolor miniature of an unidentified child.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The papers arrived at the Library filed according to correspondent and subject. The early Toole family papers were arranged chronologically, but those items from the period 1951-1979 were left in the original order by subject.
Related Material
Additional material regarding the Toole family may be found in accessions #4876,a-d.
Contents List
- Correspondence, chiefly letters to Mrs. M. J. Toole 1860-1901, 1926-1927, n.d., 4 folders (Box 1)
- Poetry, Miscellaneous Papers, and Annotated Folders 1861-1871, n.d. (Box 1)
- Toole Family Photographs 1860, 1895, n.d. (Box 1)
- Toole Family Photo Album n.d. (Box 1)
- Watercolor miniature portrait of an unidentified child n.d. (Box 1)
- Correspondence re John Toole Paintings and Toole Trust 1951-1961, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence and material re Toole exhibition in Alexandria, Virginia 1955-1958, 1975-1979, n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence re Toole-Suddarth Cemetery 1953-1958, n.d. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence and related material re Toole exhibit 1955-1978, n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence re Biography of John Toole 1960, 1972 & 1975 (Box 2)
- Charcoal drawing of a woman by John Toole n.d., Oversize Folder